Thank you.
Good morning. I've had more people come up to me before the sermon saying, "We're really looking forward to this week." So welcome to our last week on Revelation, and lower your expectations. We just have a simple sermon this morning, but I find that as I'm preparing for this, I find that I'm going to talk to you about Ezekiel, and you say, "Why, Kent? Why on the last week of Revelation with so much to cover would we be talking about Ezekiel?"
And the answer to that is because John was talking about Ezekiel, or at least he was talking in terms of Ezekiel. So we need to look at Ezekiel. So Ezekiel was an Old Testament prophet, and we've talked about Old Testament prophets this last six months, as people of great dignity, who had a position in government and significance. And Ezekiel lived at a time when the nation had been wiped out. The temple, Solomon's Grand Temple, had been torn down. The priests had been executed. The way of worshiping God
was no more. The promise of the root of David, it seemed, was lost 150 years after Isaiah had prophesied it, right? It seemed that everything that they had put their hopes in were gone, and they were living in a refugee camp on the banks of the Euphrates. And if you'd run into Ezekiel, he would have seemed like a scrubby crazy man, right? The way they describe him. And yet, as he sat here ministering to this people on the banks of the Euphrates in this refugee camp, with all their hopes and all their promise gone, having undergone tremendously,
this violence, he saw a vision of the Lord high and lifted up with the creatures of heavenly beings all about him, singing to him about his holiness as he sat on the great throne. And it seems that Ezekiel was seeing the same reality that John was seeing 700 years later, right? John also lived at a time when Rome came in and leveled the city and executed the priests. It's, Josephus tells us the line from the wall, the roads,
Jerusalem were lined with crosses of people that were killed, right? The Sea of Galilee was red with blood from the battles that went up there. It was an extraordinarily violent time. And the second temple was once again leveled. And again, there was no way to worship God in the way prescribed in the Old Testament. The sacrificial system was disrupted. And everyone had to flee from Jerusalem or die.
The Christians who fled Jerusalem just as the Jewish nation was driven out and their history and their families back in Jerusalem were now slaughtered in the time of Ezekiel. The Christians who fled Jerusalem were left without a home to return to. They were now strangers in a strange land throughout the Roman Empire. And as we discussed in our Hebrews class, for those that were in there, they had to discover how to worship God now without a temple, right? The priesthood and the assurance of the community and the future and the hope of the
Messiah coming from David were now gone and the promise was once dead, except that the Christians had found that Christ was a fulfillment of that messianic prophecy. And when they read the Old Testament, they could see how Christ actually had fulfilled it. And they had a hope. We see that explained repeatedly in the New Testament. Philip the evangelist in Acts 8 meets the Ethiopian eunuch who's reading Isaiah, and he says, "How can I possibly understand this?" And Philip explains to him that it's talking about Christ.
who had been recently crucified and risen from the dead. And he explains the whole gospel, and it's so persuasive that the eunuch wants to be baptized right then. We see on the road to Emmaus, people who were distraught after Christ's death. They can't understand what's gone wrong. And it turns out Christ, although they didn't recognize him, walks through the Old Testament prophecies and says to them, "I am the Messiah, and here's the path back to God. Here's the new way you can worship without all that you had expected looking the way you expected it to."
Even Christ himself, when he declared his messianic purpose in Luke 4, he did so by declaring the words of Isaiah and then saying, "This day in your presence, these words are fulfilled." So this is a newly uprooted community under extreme persecution, which like the community that Ezekiel served, they had cause to doubt all that God promised them if they looked just at what was going on around them.
Right now, to an extent that we don't fully understand. It is easy, I think, for probably some people in here, or it's natural, I should say, not easy, to read the revelation of all these promises of the future and say, "Yeah, but I'm looking at the world. There's floods, there's strongmen, there's rulers that are invading others and breaking. Law means nothing, and man oppresses man." That's what Revelation is telling us, right?
"In this world you will have trouble, you will have persecution, but take heart, I have overcome the world." And the people that first heard this, that believed it and passed the faith on to you, I don't want to be comparative, but they were going through extreme trouble, the likes of which we have never experienced. And this made sense to them, this was persuasive to them. This was a hope that they could live in and a hope they did not disappoint.
Everything that Satan does to try to poke holes into God's plan, no matter how much the dragon flails, right? It shows that at the end, righteousness will prevail. The kingdom of heaven is triumphant. Christ is always at the center of these visions that we see in Revelation. And in the end, you know, he wins. And to be clear, it's not like he was losing at halftime and staged a comeback, right? He wins because he was always triumphant. The dragon never had a chance, right?
Unveiling and trying to harm God, and God takes his time to try to get all of us back from the dragon, right? That's what's going on. And the kingdom of heaven will land. And the revelation then, the unveiling, the apocalypse, the unveiling of what we're seeing is the unveiling of the world to come. It's the unveiling of this plan that he began at the time of Christ and that he consummated in the vision that John saw in Revelation.
A week ago, or ten weeks ago, sorry. I said, "I hope that everyone here will get a renewed perspective on Revelation and see it as a letter of promise that Christ has overcome the world." Yeah, there's tribulation, but Christ has overcome the world. And I said that this is a letter which, according to the author, as part of that, expects to affect our behavior.
In chapter one, I asked you to discover how you can live in accordance with this book, as it says in chapter one, verse four. John said, "This is a letter aimed at
Jesus' servants who need to keep, or heed, or obey, or take to heart Shema, hear and obey the words of this prophecy." And I asked you guys, "What does that mean?" And to look at Revelation, not with the question, "What's going to happen to me?" But with the question, "How can I keep the words of this book?" Right? And I want to thank you, because you guys gave me very thoughtful responses to that. I got a number of responses of people saying, "Here's how I can keep the words of this book." And I should tell you, they were completely anonymous.
I have no idea who said anything. There's no email addresses. I didn't really try to track them, but I couldn't have. I just got sort of the text of your answers. And the response is, as a group, one thing that stood out was that you guys adopted from this series two strong images. One is the slain lamb at the center of everything that you're following, and that's tremendous. And the other thing you adopted was the idea of the fallen and flailing dragon, right, who's pitching a hissy fit and hurting us, right?
Specifically, I'm going to read you a few of responses I got. Someone said, "I've been impressed by the weight of God's holiness and the power of his sovereignty. These two things are calling me to live more faithfully and confidently and peacefully in the middle of whatever turmoil is going on around me." That is a lesson of revelation. These people are going through tremendous turmoil, and they were learning to live. God will, he says, in some way already has accomplished his redemptive plan. A second person said that extremely succinctly.
He's coming back. Stay focused on him. He has the victory over evil. He's coming back soon. I thought that was pretty good. That's a summary of the book. If you get that out of it, you've done well.
This last one I'm going to read you was very personal. I think this person really got what I was asking, saying, "How am I specifically going to do this? How am I going to keep the words of this book?"
I think Revelation has been asking me to feed my faith in very simple but steady practices of staying in his word, drawing deeper in prayer,
regular repentance. It's been a season of suffering and pain, and this study has challenged me to turn my questions of why into questions of how can I be faithful to Jesus in this season and at every season of life, and who is he forming me to be even through pain and suffering?
Turn your questions of why, all the people that are going through persecution at that time, turn their questions of why is this happening into how can I be faithful? How can I follow the Lamb?
That's the question, and that's the question that all the speakers up here this summer have addressed, and I've sort of coalesced all the things we've said into what I hope are two representative points of how you can be faithful.
The first one is we've said, "Live as citizens of the new creation now. Know that your choices today are reflected into what's happened in eternity," right?
Mark says that, you know, Christ will come in the final judgment. Like a thief in the night, that doesn't mean he's going to steal anything. It means you're going to be asleep and it's going to happen all of a sudden, right? You're not going to see it coming.
And so you can't get ready. You've got to be ready. Stay ready so you don't have to get ready, right?
So we're told in Jesus' parables about having our robes washed, being ready for the wedding supper when the call, when the invitation comes.
That's what we're talking about. It's going to happen all of a sudden. We won't have time to get ready, and so we have to be prepared.
And when I say prepared, it is important when we're talking about Revelation, when we're being prepared, we are not preparing for the tribulation.
We are preparing for the new Jerusalem, right? You're preparing for when Christ comes again, and heaven and earth are reunited, and we're there in the presence of God.
Are you ready to stand revealed in his presence? Is your robe washed? There's going to be tribulation.
In this world, we'll have tribulation, but take heart, I've overcome the world. You're going to get past it.
And when you get past it, God will be on the other side, and are you ready to meet him? That is how you stay prepared.
And the second practical way of then doing that, how do you be ready for them, is to avoid getting tangled up in the current system of corruption and the powers that man creates, right?
The dragon, it shows in Revelation, constantly counterfeits what God has and attempts to pull you away and let you follow your appetites and your cravings and your idolatry instead of God.
He competes for our worship and our allegiance. And as Sam pointed out last week, chapters 17 and 18, we see that Babylon is neither as indomitable nor as permanent as it pretends to be, or as it feels to us.
We feel like it's the water we swim in. There's nothing but this culture that constantly, slowly erodes and pulls us away from the way of Christ.
That's temporary, right? We see in John's vision that all of Babylon is thrown into the ocean like a millstone into the sea, and it's gone.
And after that is the new Jerusalem, and God's there, and there's a final judgment. So focus your loyalties and leave your idols, right, so that you're ready, so that your robes are clean.
How do we remain faithful? We follow the lamb wherever he goes. That's how we remain faithful.
In John's vision, when the witnesses have done that, when the martyrs have done that, and they followed the lamb, and Babylon is thrown down, what happens, right?
What can we expect to happen next? Well, very briefly, I'm going to summarize chapters 19 and 20.
What happens after these things, when Babylon is thrown down, is there's a big celebration, right? Everybody's happy.
The multitude sings hallelujah around the throne, the harlot is judged, and the almighty reigns.
The marriage supper of the lamb occurs, the bride arrives ready and adorned, and everyone who has fine, clean linens is invited in.
It's this tremendous celebration. And who shows up but the rider on the white horse, right?
And it's Jesus from chapter one with the sword in his mouth, king of kings and Lord of lords, glowing and fully glorified.
He's done a charmed king and king of lords, lords now on a horse, ready for battle.
And he has blood on his robe from the sacrifice that's been made and from the conflict.
And as when he arrives, the beast and the prophet are thrown down.
There is a time of the martyrs being honored for what they've done, reigning with Christ,
after which Satan is thrown down permanently. He's gone.
Then there's a judgment at the white throne, and all those who followed their cravings and followed their idols
and therefore their names aren't ready in the land of the book of life, meaning they are not prepared to stand with a holy God
because they've chosen a way of not being holy. They're judged for their deeds, and they are thrown down.
And finally, even death and Hades are thrown down. So what happens after Babylon is thrown down?
Those who stood with Christ are able to continue doing that, but the beast, the prophet, the harlot, Satan,
those who chose idolatry and death and Hades are all thrown down.
It even says in verse 11 that the old heaven and the old earth had no place now before God and His holiness revealed,
and they fled away. So everything except God and the people who've been following Him have just been thrown down.
It's gone. Sort of an empty space. And that's where we are when we get to the beginning of chapter 21.
And John says, "Then I saw a new heaven and a new earth, for the first heaven and the first earth had passed away,
and the sea was no more." We've talked about the sea being primordial chaos, right?
These people lived at a place where the Dead Sea was. The Dead Sea is still there.
It's a place that everything that touches it dies. It's salty. It's briny. It's not refreshing.
And they understood that that depth of death that Jonah thought he was dragged down and down into,
or Sheol was at the bottom, and that ocean which would rise up as in the time of Noah to destroy God's good creation, right?
All of that is gone. The only thing that's left is living water.
Verse 2, "And I saw the holy city, New Jerusalem, coming down out of heaven from God,
prepared as a bride adorned for her husband, meaning completely unsullied, bright and clean."
And this echoes, of course, the wedding supper of the Lamb parable of Christ,
as well as the frequent reference to us being the bride of Christ in New Testament writing.
And then in verse 3, "And I heard a loud voice from the throne saying,
Behold, the dwelling place or the tabernacle of God is with man.
He will dwell with them, and they will be his people, and God himself will be with them as their God."
This tabernacling among man echoes a tremendous train of promise from the Old Testament.
We first see it in Exodus 25 when God is telling Moses how to build the tabernacle
based on a pattern of the heavenly temple.
It's a place where it was called the Tent of Meeting because it's where they would come to meet God.
God set up this tent because they were nomadic people, so he told them to build it with the materials they had at hand.
So he built a tent in the shape of a temple, and he would meet them there.
There was a fence around it. You would never go inside the fence unless it was on holy business, profane business, stayed outside.
Then there was an altar where you could offer sacrifices to get yourself right with God.
There was a labor where you would cleanse yourself to get yourself clean.
And then if you are in very holy business, you would go into the temple, into the holy place, and minister before God.
And once a year, the high priest, having gone through tremendous ablutions and with great humility, went into the Holy of Holies,
this final room where the ark of God stayed, and they understood that to be his footstool, right?
Heaven can't even contain you, and the earth is your footstool.
But this is the place we can meet you in this holy reserved space, the Holy of Holies.
And that is where God would come and meet with the high priest, and he would be their God, and they would be his people.
And they would live their lives around him, and he would dwell among them in this way.
It talks about Exodus and Ezekiel and Kings and Chronicles. Every time they put up a new temple or a tabernacle,
it's how the presence of God would fill that temple so that they could meet him there.
"And he will dwell among them, and they shall be his people," is a refrain that's echoed in Leviticus and Ezekiel,
Jeremiah, Exodus. But it's also echoed in John 1:14, where the living luminous word of God, Christ,
he came and tabernacled, he came and dwelt among us, and we beheld his glory, the glory of God the Father,
full of grace and truth. And Jesus tells us in John 14:23, "For those who love me and keep my word,
I will make my abode with them. I will make my tabernacle with them." He was claiming to be
the footprint of holiness on earth that we could live our lives around, as the temple had been.
And in verse 4 then, as the bride of Christ comes down, and God says, "I will be your God, and you'll be my people."
Verse 4, "He will wipe away every tear from their eyes, and death shall be no more; neither shall there be mourning,
nor crying, nor pain anymore; for the former things have passed away. The old earth is gone."
This would be a tremendous salve, a word very much needed by people going through this persecution.
People who had just, as they were reading this in the following years, they had seen their temple torn down,
and their priests executed. For the ones, the martyrs who had been persecuted, and those who had lost Jerusalem.
Following this, the one from the throne declares, "He who was seated on the throne says, 'Behold, I'm making all things new.'"
He also said, "Write this down, for these words are trustworthy and true."
And he said to me, "It is done. I am the Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the end."
Making all things new is a reference back to the third page of the Bible, Genesis 3.
When he'd made an Eden, and God was living with man, but we messed up, Adam messed up, and we were separated from God out of the garden.
And now he's making all things new again, right?
He's making things that had been old. He's remaking them fresh and anew.
And saying that he's the Alpha and Omega, first of all, reminds us of his eternality.
He was there at that time in Genesis 3, and he's there at the end in Revelation.
He's the Alpha and the Omega. But it's also language used by Isaiah, starting in Isaiah 41.
To reference, he's there at the beginning and end of the redemptive work.
Whenever Isaiah used the phrase, "He's the first and the last," it's in the context of redemption.
So, in Isaiah 41, "I'll make all things new. I will be your redeemer," Isaiah says in 44.
But in 48, when he uses this phrase again, he's talking about Israel as a stiff-necked people,
and that they're going to have to go through a refining fire.
They're going to have to go through persecution, and then he will deliver them after they've been refined and comfort them
and pay double and win them back. I've made you, and then I pay to get you back.
I was there at the beginning of that as the Alpha. I'm there at the end of that as the Omega, the beginning and the end.
This thing that Isaiah promised is happening in the vision of John, right?
It's the thing they've been waiting for, for years and years.
In verse 7 then, I'm sorry, continuing in verse 6,
"To the thirsty I will give from the spring of water of life without payment."
Again, the spring of water of life is something that's referenced throughout the Old Testament, throughout the prophets.
We're going to come back to it in a minute because he talked about it more in chapter 22, but it's very significant.
"And to the one who conquers," says the one on the throne, "they will have heritage, and I will be his God, and he will be my son."
Leave behind the current conflict over language and gender politics.
When he says son there, it's applying to everyone in the room, independent of your sex, right?
Son is the language of inheritance. Son is the language of having position in this new kingdom.
You're not there as a citizen. You're not there as a servant. You're there as a son. You have ownership.
And we know that because he says, "We'll have heritage. I will be his God, and he will be my son."
But as for the cowardly, the faithless, the detestable, as for murderers, the sexually immoral, sorcerers, idolaters, and liars,
these are the people that chose their appetites and their cravings and idolatry sitting in Babylon over Christ, right?
They've not prepared for the marriage supper of the Lamb, and here they are, and it's too late.
They don't have time to get prepared. Their portion will be in the lake that burns with fire and sulfur, which is the second death.
And then in verse 9, he says, "Then came one of the seven angels who has had the seven bowls full of the seven last plagues,
and he spoke to me saying, 'Come, I will show you the bride, the wife of the Lamb.'"
It's almost a comical moment because an eternal angel, that's a present active participle.
He's got the bowl, right? So he's walking over to him with a bowl of God's wrath that's just destroyed a third of the earth,
saying, "Hey, man, that would be terrifying," right? But in this moment, he's not.
And I believe the reason John put that little detail in there is that's no longer a threat, right?
It's no longer a danger in this new heaven and new earth. He's got the bowl.
And incidentally, these bowls, they look like small veggie trays from a party, you know,
just sort of shallow with a little thing in the middle so you could hold on to them.
And they were used for pagan libations, for pouring out drink offerings to the gods.
And the image here is of God pouring his wrath back out on them for all the idolatry, right?
And so now he's got this instrument of God's wrath, and it doesn't matter anymore.
He's like, "Hey, I've got something great to show you."
And they go and they see the beauty of the bride of Christ coming down.
"And he carried me away to a high mountain and showed me the holy city of Jerusalem coming down out of heaven,
having the glory of God, its radiance like a most rare jewel, like Jasper, like a crystal."
And it just describes it a bit. And then in verse 15, "And the one who spoke with me had a measuring rod,
of gold to measure the city and its gates and its walls, the city lies four square.
It's length the same as its width. And he measured the city with his rod.
It was 1,200 stadia. Some of your Bibles probably say 1,500 miles, roughly the same distance.
Its length and its width and its height are equal."
So, he's just gone through this whole thing that I skipped through, where he's describing the beauty of the city.
Streets like glass, but sort of like gold. Walls like minerals, beautiful gemstones, but transparent.
The gates like giant pearls. It's on 12 foundation stones, one for each of the saints, because it's founded on the faithful, those who've been faithful.
It's got a gate for each of the 12 tribes of Israel to match the stones on the high priest's breastplate,
because those who have always worshipped him are still welcome, right?
It's still founded on those who've been faithful to him. And in talking about all this beauty, he says,
"And here's the dimensions of the wall." Why would he do that? Who cares?
Ah, well, there's an answer. Okay, I'll tell you who cares.
In verse 15, he calls out the golden measuring rod as a deliberate reference back to Ezekiel, right?
In Ezekiel 40, after the better part of seven chapters, Ezekiel has walked around the eternal temple
with this guy who has a measuring rod, measuring out the entire pattern so that they know what it's like.
Ezekiel lived at a time when the temple had just been leveled, and everybody's hope was gone.
And he's telling them, "This doesn't matter. The tabernacle's gone. This temple's gone.
But the eternal temple remains. We know exactly what it's like. We can rebuild it.
It's just a place where we can meet God, and that's what we want," right?
So he's gone through this whole measuring process with the measuring rod.
The people at John's time have lost their temple, and he's making a direct call back to that.
We have this guy with the measuring rod who's showing us through the eternal city, right?
Not a temple this time, city. We'll come back to that.
And so after, and incidentally, I have some compassion for the translators here that told you 1,500 miles
because you don't know what a stadia is, right? And they're just trying to help you understand this is immense.
It's a gigantic place, 1,500 miles on a side. But the 12,000 stadia is significant because it's 1,012.
Everything about the city is built on the fulfillment of God's promise: 12 apostles, 12 tribes, 12,000 stadia on a side.
Which is, incidentally, in Exodus 26, when we first hear the Holy of Holies described, when God gave this pattern to Moses to build the temple,
he told them to make the Holy of Holies 10 cubits square. This is a cubit, because carpenters in the old times carried their arms around.
They didn't have production-made rulers. So that's a cubit. It's about 18 inches. So 10 cubits is about 15 feet.
So it's a 15-foot cube. That is the only cube in the Bible. Every time you see a cube, it's the Holy of Holies, okay?
And you're fortunate here in the DC area, you can go to the Bible Museum, and if you go on the tour of the Old Testament,
you'll come without explanation or announcement into a room that's 15 feet cube.
And you'll see that they've hung a light just in the middle of it, 7 1/2 feet from the wall, 7 1/2 feet from the floor.
In the very center of this room would have been the Shekinah glory of God as it sat over the Ark of the Covenant that sat in the middle of the floor.
So as the high priest came in, he would look up, and the holiness of God would be there as he walked in with great humility into his presence.
And the Hebrew scholars understood holy, holy, holy to be God filling our three-dimensional space.
And he sits in the middle and emanates to the entire edge of the room as holiness pervades everything, and you're now soaked in it.
This is what we're getting ready for, right? The holiness of God.
And that's how Moses saw it, this 15-foot cube.
When Ezekiel went with the measuring rod, it was now, I'm sorry, when Solomon built the temple, he made it twice the size.
He made it 30-foot square so that, you know, the presence of God would be 15 feet in the air, as it were.
And when Ezekiel saw it, it was now measured with royal cubits, and it was 35 feet cubed, right?
So we have this ever-expanding, every time we see the Holy of Holies, it's getting a little bigger.
And now we get to John, and if you're wondering why a city coming out of the sky is cubed, who lives in a cube, right?
It's because the entire city is the Holy of Holies.
This is what he's showing you. It's not 35 cubits square, it's 350,000 cubits square, right?
And it says in verse 22, "I saw the temple by 23, and the city has no need of sun or moon to light it,
for the glory of God gives its light, and the lamp is the Lamb. And by its light nations will walk,
and the kings of the earth will bring their glory into it. All the glory of everyone else is subsumed into the glory of God,
who's high and lifted up on his throne, the throne of Jesus, the Lamb at the center of this Holy of Holies."
And the entire world is now inside the Holy of Holies. There's nothing separating us from God anymore.
And it says that the gates of the city are never locked, because there's never any threat. It says they're never locked by day,
and oh, by the way, there's no night, right? Because it's only God's presence. We no longer have sun or moon,
we just have God in this new heaven and new earth. And the new heaven and new earth are the same place,
and they're all inside the Holy of Holies, which is all just to say we have been brought into his holiness.
Right? In this end vision. I have no idea where we are in these notes.
He will be our temple. Right, so Jerusalem was destroyed. We see that He will be our temple,
and we will be restored to Him as we were in Eden. Heaven on earth, the new earth and the old earth has passed away.
Moses and Ezekiel and now John were all shown the eternal temple, after which the temple and the tabernacle
were patterned, so that He could dwell among us and the people could arrange their lives around Him.
The Gospel of John tells us that Christ, the Word of God, became fleshed and made His tabernacle among us,
and He became the living tabernacle around whom we could arrange our lives, and we beheld His glory,
the glory of the only begotten of the Father, full of greats and truths.
And now John is foretelling us that in this final day, all the earth and all our glories and all our ambitions
will be subsumed in His presence, which it says in where all the kings will come.
Here all the kings will come before Him, and they will bring into it their glory and the honor of all their nations,
and nothing unclean will ever enter this temple, this city.
In verse 18 and 20, it talks about how the city is made of pure gold that's clear like glass,
which gold isn't, right? And it talks about how the walls are made of crystal gems and jasper that's clear like glass,
which of course gems aren't, at least not jasper. And he talks about how the gates were one single pearl.
John is just struggling to convey to us the preciousness and magnificence of this city, right?
This is not about the scarcity or the market value of gold. This isn't an opulent statement.
This is, they lived at a time when there was no HVAC, there were no preservatives, and gold seemed almost miraculous
because it never tarnished. It was always shiny and pretty, and it always kept itself.
And he's saying it was like that, but transparent. The whole city was made of it, right? It seems almost miraculous.
Anyway, on a side note, when you hear this, see this, and it says "like glass," they'd never heard of plate glass.
There was no such thing as a sheet of glass you could look through. That hadn't been developed yet.
Blowing glass had only been around for like a hundred years or less.
So a glass thing, glass-shaped thing, was an extremely rare, valuable thing that only the most wealthy king could afford
and that only the most skilled artisans could create. So glass was rare.
When they say glass, they're thinking of beads and naturally occurring lava rocks, right?
So you've got to picture like Scrooge McDuck sitting on a pile of diamonds, right?
That's when they say it looked like just sheets of lots of glass, a field of glass.
That's what they're thinking about, because that's the only way they've ever seen glass.
It's a precious, shiny, refractive thing.
So we see this city that's arranged like the tabernacle. It's founded on the faithful.
The gates evoke the high priest. And it's not a city. I mean, it's not a temple. It's a city.
Because the only thing left is the Holy of Holies, where they've come to dwell with God, not with fear and trembling once a year, but constantly.
Just revealed before His holiness. In His holiness, His glory pervades the entire city.
The glory of God, not the sun or the moon, and all men are subjected to it.
At which point, we get to chapter 22.
Then the angel showed me the river of the water of life, brightest crystal flowing from the throne of God.
And the Lamb through the, the throne of God and the Lamb through the middle of the streets of the city.
Also, on either side of the river, the tree of life with its twelve kinds of fruit, yielding its fruit each month.
The leaves of the tree were to bring healing to the nations. And you shouldn't picture a tree that's somehow split on both sides of the river.
There's trees growing on both sides of the river. The tree of life has multiple trunks here, right?
Remember, there's no more sea, right? There's only fresh water.
This is a living river of grace, a river of living water. And this is the same river that was seen by Ezekiel.
After eight chapters of going through with that guy measuring the city, with the measuring rod, to get the temp, the pattern of the temple.
In verse 47, chapter 47 of Ezekiel, "The man brought me back to the entrance of the temple, and I saw water coming out from under the threshold of the temple toward the east," because it faced east.
It was just a little trickling out from the south side of that entrance. "And as the man went eastward with a measuring rod in his hand, he measured off a thousand cubits and then led me through water that was now ankle deep."
"Started as a trickle, now ankle deep." "He measured off another thousand cubits and led me through water that was now knee deep."
"He measured off another thousand cubits and led me through the water that was up to the waist." "He measured off another thousand cubits, but now it was a river that I could not cross."
"This is an ever-expanding river of grace that starts as a trickle and expands to fill the entire world."
"It's available to everyone, coming out of the temple with God's grace."
"It was a river that no one could cross." "Then he led me back to the banks of the river, and when I arrived there, I saw a great number of trees on either side of the river."
"And he said to me, 'This water flows down the eastern region down to the Araba, which is a desert, where it enters the Dead Sea.'"
"Dead lands, Dead Sea, and when it empties into the sea, the salty water there becomes fresh, and swarms of living creatures will live wherever the river flows."
"This river will wipe away the sea."
"It's going to convert the Dead Sea and the primordial chaos into a living grace, the living water that will infill us all."
Verse 12, "Fruit trees of all kinds grow on the banks of the river, and their leaves will not wither, nor will their fruit fail."
"Every month they will bear fruit because the water from the sanctuary flows to them, and their fruit will serve for food and their leaves for healing."
I'm going to read John again.
"The angel showed me the river that flowed out from the throne of God and of the Lamb through the middle of the street, and on either side of the river the tree of life with its twelve kinds of fruit yielding fruit each month.
The leaves of the tree were for the healing of the nations, and no longer would anything there be accursed."
Beautiful.
It clearly brings to mind other words from Christ in the gospel as he sat in Samaria with the woman at the well.
John 4, he says, "Whoever drinks of the water that I give them shall never be thirsty, but the water that I give him will become in him a fountain of water springing up to eternal life.
It will grow in you and spring over to others."
John 7:37, he cried out, "If anyone is thirsty, let him come to me and drink.
The one who believes in me, as the Scripture said, from his innermost being will flow out rivers of living water.
All of this is referencing Isaiah, chapters 44, 55, and 58, where he promises that waters of grace will come at no cost, what John keeps saying, the water at no cost.
And it will restore the earth and flow out of those who are restored.
So this is a picture of us imbibing the water of life flowing out of the temple, which is now, Christ is the temple, right?
God and the Lamb are the temple. There was no temple. It was God and the Lamb who are now the temple.
The water is flowing out from under them, as it had been from the temple.
It's filling us, it's filling the whole earth, and overflowing to others.
And so we have a promise of this return to an Edenic state from the third page of the Bible,
where we can live with God, where verse 3, there's no longer any curse.
But the throne of God and the Lamb will be in it, and His servants will worship Him, and they will see His face, and His name will be on their foreheads,
which the beast had tried to counterfeit. And the night will be no more, and there will be no need of lamp or sun,
for the Lord God will be there as their light, and they will reign forever and ever with the Lord high and lifted up,
and us basking in His glory. It is a beautiful, beautiful promise.
So how do we live in light of these things? That's the question. How do we keep the words of this prophecy?
John tells us two ways, specifically, that we can do that. In verse 17 of this last chapter, he says,
"Let anyone who is thirsty come, and let the one who desires take the water of life without cost."
That's thing one, right? You imbibe of the water, let it grow in you. As you know, it fills up, it grows, it grows,
and spills out to those around you. So you both imbibe and become a source of the water of life to the world,
which will overcome the sea and bring things back to life.
In verse 14, he said, "Blessed are those who wash their robes,
so that they will have the right to the tree of life, and they may enter the city by the gates."
Wash your robe, live in loyalty to him, be purified, have a clean robe ready, and drink deeply of the water of light.
That is literally how you keep the words of this prophecy, according to John.
However we understand this book, Donna talked this morning about how it's been, for some people, a totally new perspective on this book,
but however you understand this book, those two things are true, and you should do those two things.
I first learned to associate this book with the song, "I Wish We'd All Been Ready."
Two men walking up the hill, one is taken, one left standing still, "I Wish We'd All Been Ready."
It is an ominous and fearful view of this book.
We should associate this book with songs about God's holiness.
The creatures and the angels and the saints around the throne sing, "Holy, holy, holy is the Lord God Almighty."
As they surround the glorious throne of the eternal king.
And the tribulation is not their focus, and the beast is not their focus, and the wrath and the bulls and the four horsemen is not their focus.
The slain lamb who conquered all with the final sacrifice, that's the focus.
He is holy.
He paid the debt we could not pay for our sins to close the gap we could not cross between the profane and the holy.
And Revelation is about that gap disappearing.
The gates of the new Jerusalem will always be open.
There will no longer be any night.
There will no longer be any curse of sin from Genesis 3.
Heaven and earth will be renewed and come together, where all the earth is blessed with his holy presence.
This was created for but then abandoned by Adam, re-promised to Abraham and Moses, glimpsed by Ezekiel as the present reality,
when things seemed darkest to his people and most broken.
The cure was instantiated through Christ and his sacrificial gift, and it seemed consummated here in John's vision.
In this vision, God isn't saying anything new, I think someone during this series said.
He's saying the same thing that he said over and over and over.
Jesus taught us to ask for this daily.
He said, "You should pray our Father who art in heaven, hallowed be thy name."
We were just told that the one sitting on the throne high and lifted up in heaven has said that we will be his sons and have inheritance.
He is our Father, our holy Father in heaven.
Hallowed be thy name, that means holy is your name.
Our Father who art in heaven, hallowed be thy name.
Thy kingdom come, thy will be done.
That is what this is picturing.
His kingdom finally coming and his will done in all things.
No evil ever enters the gate, there's never night, there's never death, the sea is gone.
Forgive us our debts as we forgive our debtors.
Give us this day our daily bread, right?
That means no scarcity in this new place.
Forgive us our debts as we forgive our debtors.
That is us imbibing the water of life and then returning it to others.
It flows through us.
And lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from evil.
He just said in this kingdom, there's no more any curse, there's no more sin.
This is the picture of life in the holy city.
For yours is the kingdom and the power and the glory forever and ever.
Amen.
So be it.
He is sitting there in power and glory forever in this kingdom.
This, which is on the screen, the Lord's Prayer, is a prayer invoking the end of Revelation.
This is what we're to pray for daily.
This is our focus.
So to end our series on Revelation, I'd like to do two things.
First, I'd like us to all stand and pray the Lord's Prayer together in a way that we've never prayed it before.
Every time you pray this, you should see his promise from the end of Revelation.
And then the musicians are going to lead us in a closing song of holiness, okay?
Our Father, who art in heaven, hallowed be thy name.
Thy kingdom come, and thy will be done on earth as it is in heaven.
Give us this day our daily bread, and forgive us our debts as we forgive our debtors.
Lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from evil.
For thine is the kingdom, and the power, and the glory, forever and ever. Amen.